Hi and welcome back to another video
with it's Dr. Dan and today we're going
to be looking at marity. So marity is
the concept that you need to know to
pass chemistry and the big thing what
this has to do with is how to make
solutions meaning how do different
chemicals appear in the aquous phase or
if we have an amount of solute mixed
with a solvent. And you are probably
like what are a lot of these words?
Well, the big thing here is that we're
just trying to figure out what the
concentration is of a solution. So, if
we go down to let's say if you're in lab
and you're trying to make a solution.
So, how do you exactly do that?
Generally, you are mixing different
ingredients. So, let's say for example,
if we take a solute such as just common
sodium chloride or table salt and we
throw that into water. So if we throw
that into water that is labeled as the
solvent and the reason why these two are
labeled this way the solute is always
referred to as the minor component and
the solvent is the major component or
whatever the whatever is most uh what's
contained the most here. So if we have
our little V flask over here and we have
that NaCCl is going to dissociate. is
going to be soluble which we talked
about in a previous video regarding
solubility. So if we take sodium
chloride it's going to break down into
its two individual ions here. So we have
Na+ and Cl minus. Now how do we report
this in form of concentration? Well this
is where marity is going to come in.
So marity in this case is referred to as
the following. So when we see marity
it's always written as big m. So it's
marity and that's going to be big m. And
now the units for marity. So if we have
something like this dissociation here,
well if we read this like a chemical
formula right we have that one mole of
NAC
is dissociating to one mole of sodium
plus and one mole of chlorine. So what
better way to represent a concentration
than by moles. Now so what we will
represent this is going to be moles of
our solute over
the volume of our solvent.
Okay, so moles over volume. Now, being
that this is a volume, this has to be in
lers. So, if we have our volutric flask
that we're making our solution in,
that's going to be in L. Whereas our
solute, this is going to be moles of our
solute. Now whenever we have this so
being that this is a sodium chloride one
another way for us to represent this
which is a very important nomencl or
nomenclature for us is square brackets.
So if we have a square bracket around
let's say NaCCl
this is referring to the concentration
of NaCCl
aka the marity so that's concentration
so that's moles so that could be moles
of NaCCl
for every liter of NaCCl
or sorry liter of water in this case
being that that's our solvent so moles
of NaCCl is a solute over lers of water
as our sol solvent. Okay, so solute and
solvent
solute
solvent.
Now being that said, let's try a couple
practice problems putting this into
place so that way we can see how exactly
we're going to be using this as a
formula for ourselves. So if I ask you
the following one, what is the marity of
a solution prepared with 125 g of sodium
chloride and 250
ml of water. So with this right we have
to identify all the important piece of
information. So if we look at this
quickly we can see okay we have 125 g of
solution here. So that's going to be one
piece of information. Then we also have
250 ml of water. So when we are doing
this, we need to be able to label okay,
what is the solute? What is the solvent?
Now in 99% of your situations, water is
most likely going to be your solvent in
general chemistry. So this one here is
going to be our solvent,
which is going to be in the denominator,
and this will be our solute. Now, I
wrote this out into simple steps how we
can do these problems. So the first
thing that we're going to do is we're
going going to convert the mass to moles
being that marity if you remember is
moles over lers. So we need to plug in
our different components. So if we take
that 125 g
of NaCCl,
we're going to once again do a little
conversion tool for ourselves. We're
going to set this up like a tea table.
So we will write have that written out
for ourselves. Now in order to cancel
grams what is always the step to do
that. So if you can kind of remember
with every one of these right if you're
going to be converting mass to moles in
order to do that we need to use molar
mass to do that conversion. So this is
something that involves a lot of
stoeometry
when you are trying to solve for marity.
So we will look up that molar mass for
sodium chloride. And after you look that
up, you'll see that 1 mole of sodium
chloride is equivalent to 58.44
g of NaCCl.
And that is taking that directly from
your periodic table. Now g of NaCCl
cancels g of NaCCl. So those two things
are going to cancel as a result leaving
us only with moles. So when we solve
that, we will see that we have 2.14
moles of NaCCl,
which is going to be plugged in
eventually to our molar formula as the
solute.
Okay, but we're not done yet. Before we
can plug that in, we have to convert
volume to L. Being that we started this
problem with 250
ml of water, we must convert this. So
going back to our dimensional analysis,
we can easily convert to this from 250
ml of water
to L. So we have to look up what is that
conversion from L to milliliters. And
one thing you might be able to remember
is that 1,000 milliliters is 1 liter. So
milliliters will be cancelled
and that will leave us only with lers of
water as a result. So 250 / 1,000 and
that's going to give you 0.250
L of water.
All right. So now that we have these two
pieces of information, the next thing
we're going to do is calculate marity.
So how do we do that? Well, if you
remember just to write down the formula
again, marity was moles of solute
over the volume of solvent.
So, which is equal to m. Now, we want to
know what the concentration is of sodium
chloride. So, what we're going to do is
we're going to plug in all those
individual pieces. We had 2.14 moles of
sodium chloride and.250
L of water. So we'll take both those
numbers and we're going to pretty much
plug these in like it is just a normal
formula like you have from gas laws or
from any other part of the class like or
heat or energy to do this conversion.
All right. So now I have that 214 moles
of sodium chloride over.250
L. And this is going to be a very quick
division for ourselves. And we will get
that with 8.56
molar NaCCl
which you can also represent saying this
in square brackets for sodium chloride
which is our answer for this example.
Now let's try to do another one. There's
a couple different scenarios where this
can be shown. So let's try to do
another. So what if I ask you the
following? What is the concentration of
hydroxide
from barium hydroxide if 75.2 g is added
to 500 L of water? Okay, what does that
refer to? Well, acidbased chemistry is a
very big part of concentrations in
solutions. So, if we are to have this,
we need to first understand what is the
chemical formula look like when it's
added to water. How does the solubility
work? So if I take berium hydroxide and
I add that to water, how is it going to
break down into its most basic ions? How
is the cat ions and the annions going to
be breaking apart? So the first thing is
is that I have one barium ion, so Ba2+
and then two hydroxide ions that are
going to be breaking apart as a result.
And don't forget that that subscript
here gets turned into a coefficient. So
being showing that we're breaking it
down into all of its ions.
When that happens, one thing that we're
going to be doing now is writing out our
conversion. So we need to go from mass
of berium hydroxide
to moles of hydroxide. So we have to do
a few steps of our conversion. So the
first thing is is whenever we convert
from mass we need to cancel out the
units. So how would we exactly do that?
Well and bridge that gap to moles well
we would use the molar mass. So we
always write out our units like a plan
for ourselves. So that way we can see
all right this is this is the steps I
need to take.
So grams of berium hydroxide will cancel
out g of berium hydroxide. Now we need
to look up our molar mass for berium
hydroxide.
And after you calculate that, so for one
barium, two oxygen, two hydrogens, what
we're going to be getting is 171.34
g for every 1 mole of berium hydroxide.
Now, we're not done yet, though. We have
to now calculate how much hydroxide,
which this is where it comes from our
solubility equation. There are two moles
of hydroxide for every one mole of
berium hydroxide molecule here. So when
we do this, we're going to take 75.2
divide it by 171.34
* 2 and what we are going to get for our
final numbers is 0.878
moles
of hydroxide.
So this is telling you how much base
equivalent you have in solution or how
much hydroxide is ready to react here.
Now what we're now going to do is
convert volume once again to liters.
Right? We want to be able to plug all
these individual components into marity.
So we had 500 uh 500 milliliters in the
original problem and I realized I wrote
liters by accident. So 500 milliliters
that would be a lot of liquid. So if we
have that 500 ml, we'll convert that
once again to L. So 1,000
milliliters is equivalent to 1 L
millilit is going to be canceling out
and what we're going to be left with is
0.500
L and we keep our sigfigs.
So now that we have both of these
numbers, what are these representing?
Well, this is our solute. This is our
solvent.
And now we're going to be putting them
into our marity equation for our last
step. So, just a kind of a little
reminder, right? We want to figure out
the concentration of hydroxide. That's
going to be moles of hydroxide
all over the L of water. Okay. So, being
that we have our moles of hydroxide,
that's going to that was our first
number we calculated, which was 0.87.
moles of hydroxide
all divided by 0.500
L of water.
So when that is all said and done, we
will have 1.76
molar of hydroxide. And we could also
represent that in square brackets as
well. just show it this way which this
would be our final answer. Okay.
So if I ask you one more problem, let's
say if we wanted to do a different type.
Let's say you wanted to make a solution,
which is a very common thing that you
have to do in a general chemistry lab.
So if I asked you how many grams of
sodium nitrate are required to make a
250 ml solution
that is 2.14 molar how would you do it?
So being that we want to make a solution
how are we going to go about that so the
first thing is you need to figure out
how much volume do you need of this? Do
you want to make a liter half a liter?
What exactly are you doing? So I told
you all right 250
milliliters that's the first step. So
what we're going to do is we're going to
convert that to lers.
So be 250 / 1,000 * 1 L. And what that's
going to convert that to is 0.250
L.
Now why do we care about that? Well, in
order to convert marity to moles, we
need L. So being that we have 2.14
marity as our term here that also
represents 2.14 moles all over one
liter. So in order to calculate how much
how many moles we have we have to
multiply this by the the amount of
solution we have. So if I do this where
I take that 250 L cancel out those two
units we'll be left with only the amount
of moles here.
So be 2.14
*.25
and what we are going to be getting is
0.535
moles of sodium nitrate. Now does that
give you your g? Well if you think back
to stochometry to go from moles to g we
got to use thear mass again. So in this
case we'll do one last step
of converting moles of sodium nitrate
by tsing it by its molar mass. So the
molar mass of sodium nitrate once we
kind of write that thing down it's going
to be 84.997
g of sodium nitrate.
This is going to cancel out. So, moles
of sodium nitrate cancels moles of
sodium nitrate, leaving us with our
mass. So, if you wanted to make this,
you would need to add 45.47
g of sodium nitrate
to 250 ml of water to make this
solution. So not only can you figure out
the concentration of something but you
can also figure out what your mass is.
So why is this important? So with my
final sendoff point marity is a
conversion term which is extremely
powerful. So being that is said if you
go back to my solubility stochometry
videos this is painting a picture of how
we can convert and predict things. So
before when we went over stochometry,
one of the big concepts was that we
could go from mass to moles to moles to
mass, right? So when we were looking at
this entire picture, we could convert
that and that's what we did with a bunch
of these previous examples. However, we
can now bring in one more thing with
solution chemistry, which is filling in
the bottom part of this is that oh, if
we have a volume of our solution, so if
we have two test tubes of solution that
we're mixing together, well, I can now
take that volume of one of my reagents,
convert it to moles, and now I can
either convert it to a mass of my other
reactants, or I can do my mole to mole
ratio and get to my a mass, get to
volume. It allows us to do more
stoeometry equations. So marity
here is a conversion term that can be
used to our advantage. So keep that in
mind. Marity is something that can be
used as a conversion term in order to
get to volume of solutions. So this is
for solution chemistry and this is going
to be a future video where we go through
a few examples doing this. So please uh
please feel free to like and subscribe
so you see when that video comes out in
the next few weeks and hopefully this
helped you a little bit understand
solution chemistry a little bit more.
This has been Dr. Dan and I hope to see
you in around for future videos. Thank
you so much for listening and watching.
Bye now.